<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mmanu Chaturvedi&#39;s blog.</title>
  <subtitle>This is where Mmanu writes.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/" />
  <updated>2025-09-22T02:30:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Mmanu Chaturvedi</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>How the origin of everything is from its complement</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/017/" />
    <updated>2025-09-22T02:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/017/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In order for any idea or material thing to be analyzed, i.e. understood with the mind, there has to be an abstract representation of it.  And as soon as an abstraction is created in our minds, there has to be a complement of the abstraction, in order for the abstraction to exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, let&#39;s say we want to analyze a pencil.  We will first create an abstract representation of the pencil in our minds, this can vary from person to person, but they have an abstraction for the pencil in their minds, nonetheless.  When that abstraction matches with an object, they call it a pencil.  Now, the complement of the pencil is the absence of pencil, there has to exist at least one abstract representation of the absence of the pencil.  Maybe it is the pencil-sized emptiness in the pencil box, maybe it&#39;s the empty space on the desk.  But there has to exist a representation of the absence of the pencil in our minds in order for it to detect a pencil.  In other words, the origin of a pencil&#39;s presence is from its absence, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can replace &#39;pencil&#39; in the above example, with any material thing or idea, even the whole reality we perceive with our minds.  The whole reality we perceive with our minds needs to have a complement, which makes us perceive the reality as it is.  Perhaps the force which doesn&#39;t let us understand the complement of reality is what is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maya_(religion)&quot;&gt;spoken about in Advaita Vedanta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The source of knowledge</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/016/" />
    <updated>2025-09-21T02:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/016/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whether the source of all knowledge is internal or external is what we wish to address in this write-up. We define knowledge as it is defined &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge&quot;&gt;colloquially&lt;/a&gt;. By external we mean whether knowledge comes from things external to us, like books, teachers, fellow-students, etc. and by internal we mean whether knowledge comes from within us, i.e., as a reaction to the things external to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s take an example of Newton&#39;s laws of motion. Does one need an external source of knowledge to arrive at the laws of motion?  The answer is no, reproducibility is a property of Science, so one could just observe how things move and arrive at them. One doesn&#39;t need any external source of knowledge, like books or professors, in order to learn Newton&#39;s laws of motion. It&#39;s just because we wish to save time that we have external sources like books, i.e. we wish to not re-invent the wheel, so to speak, and focus on learning &amp;quot;unknown&amp;quot; laws of Nature instead of &amp;quot;known&amp;quot; ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the laws of motion, one doesn&#39;t need any external source to learn any of Nature&#39;s laws. One could learn them by observing, questioning, and reflecting.  So, the source of knowledge is internal, not external.  This post is related to the previous post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/008/&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;A perfect language&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Cornell note-taking system and different groups of people</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/015/" />
    <updated>2025-09-14T05:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/015/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/009/&quot;&gt;Cornell note-taking system&lt;/a&gt; in a previous post, and how I had found it quite an interesting way to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was wondering how it could be used to look at different kinds of people that inhabit the world. The equivalent of the main section of the notes would be the people who like to take instructions. They like to do what they are instructed to do, and what they see others doing—just taking notes. This, like the main section, would be the largest chunk of the world’s population. This population, akin to what the main section is used for, likes copying what others are doing without questioning or reflecting on it. This group is that of the common, non-scientific people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there is the group of people equivalent to the left margin. These would be the questioning types, who like to question everything consciously but do not necessarily reflect on it. This group would be like the average scientists and engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there would be the group of people who like to reflect on things but do not necessarily question them. This would be the bottom margin in the Cornell system. This group comprises of managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the group of people who like to both question things and reflect on them, on how they connect to the overall scheme of things. This group consists of the great philosophers, exceptional scientists, engineers, managers, diplomats, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How CEOs bullshit!</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/012/" />
    <updated>2025-09-05T12:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/012/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I was sharing with someone how CEOs bullshit, which led to this post. There are many videos available of CEOs of many companies announcing various things. So, it&#39;s easy to understand the thinking of CEOs at least as far as the product announcements go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s first define bullshitting. Bullshitting, for our purposes, is the opposite of being forthcoming. It&#39;s basically hiding the truth with a wrapper idea, really believing in the wrapper idea. Believing it with all your heart, to the point that you can convince everyone that the wrapper is the true intention of your actions and not the real truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that products CEOs sell are always useless. What I am saying is that there&#39;s always the real truth and the wrapper concealing it, and therein between the two lies bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now CEOs have to constantly cover the fact that they created a product because they can make a lot of money with the wrapper that the product is actually useful for society and customers. The fact that they are doing it for the money is not something that they will accept readily even when explicitly pointed out, it will be only known via the context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They will always have a complete and total belief in the product that they are selling, even if it&#39;s useless. They bullshit with total confidence their customers and listeners that it&#39;s not the fact that this product will make them profit that is the driving force but the fact that they believe that this product is useful for the customers.  They would look down upon their competition, however good that is, find faults in the competition&#39;s products and customers, make up personal stories and use other cognitive biases to promote their product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This style of bullshiting is close to how &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maya_(religion)&quot;&gt;Nature decieves us as well&lt;/a&gt;, that deserves a long write-up, though.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What the AI will not replace?</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/011/" />
    <updated>2025-09-01T16:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/011/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A discussion regarding what AI will not replace in software engineering led to
this post. AI cannot replace what it doesn&#39;t have, which is self-consciousness.
The mental manifestation of self-consciousness is reflection. And the physical
manifestation of it is the action which is taken after reflection (this, in my
opinion, is what is &#39;dharma&#39;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Dharma&#39; may mean different things in different fields. &#39;Dharma&#39; in the context of
software engineering is basically what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_McIlroy#Views_on_computing&quot;&gt;Dr. McIlroy had refered to as &#39;negative coding&#39;&lt;/a&gt;.
It&#39;s the process of removing code instead of adding it making the software simpler. (My own attempt &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/m-chaturvedi/undupes/&quot;&gt;at negative coding at design level.&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Dharma&#39; process can be explained very easily. If an action is taken without
reflection, it&#39;s not dharma, unless the instincts which are the cause of action
have been trained with the process which is created with reflection. This
process of training the instincts is commonly referred to as &#39;culture&#39;. So,
many a time, during code reviews, the software engineers would instinctually
know that a piece of code has problems. This is because of the &#39;culture&#39;, i.e.,
they have gone through so much code that they have refined their instincts with
the culture of software engineering &#39;dharma&#39;, so even without consciously
reflecting, they know that the piece of code that they are reviewing has a
problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI is trained with the latter method, that is, its &#39;instincts&#39; are being
refined to the extent that it starts doing things which come out of a lot of
reflection. So, it&#39;s trying to replicate the dharma of software engineering.
What it lacks is self-consciousness. What this means is that, unlike humans who
can remove a piece of code from what they wrote after reflecting on it, AI
cannot remove a piece of code from its own programming. That is, AI cannot do
negative coding on the code it created without interacting with any external
agents other than the code and its own programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be said in another way. Humans can evolve by just meditating like the
Buddha; a piece of program cannot just sit and evolve itself. Evolution is like
&#39;negative coding&#39;. And the final destination of &#39;negative coding&#39; is zeroness,
which, unlike the Buddha, computers cannot experience, or reach, or meditate
upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typos fixed using ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The representation of Shiva/Buddha and research</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/010/" />
    <updated>2025-08-15T04:23:15Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/010/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A discussion about why India&#39;s large investment into alternative energy will have little research outcome led to this post. The culture in India is not conducive to research, and it will never lead to good outcomes unless fundamental changes are made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The culture needed for research is like that of how the Lords Shiva and Buddha are commonly portrayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/010/unCQ_ARcAg-1920.avif 1920w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/010/unCQ_ARcAg-1920.webp 1920w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/010/unCQ_ARcAg-1920.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; width=&quot;1920&quot; height=&quot;1440&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/avif&quot; srcset=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/010/wfLypW1UDG-1006.avif 1006w&quot;&gt;&lt;source type=&quot;image/webp&quot; srcset=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/010/wfLypW1UDG-1006.webp 1006w&quot;&gt;&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; decoding=&quot;async&quot; src=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/010/wfLypW1UDG-1006.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; width=&quot;1006&quot; height=&quot;1567&quot;&gt;&lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we carefully observe the photos, we will see that the two are meditating on something, and there is absolutely no expression of any emotions. Their bodies express no emotions at all. They are not in pain or pleasure. They are not speaking. They are in a totally neutral position, but they are not asleep. The only part of their bodies that is actually expressing something are their minds, which one can only know by meditating as they do. They are, in modern parlance, conducting research on something, i.e. they are using only their minds to interact with the object of their research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indian culture at present is very emotional, without any awareness that it is so. In order to conduct any research worth speaking about, teachers and professors would have to understand and teach how to conduct research: that it must be done as Shiva and Buddha are sitting—i.e., in an emotionless way, unbiased towards results, unperturbed by expectations, listening only to Nature. Until this is taught in schools and colleges, I don&#39;t see why pouring any amount of money would lead to proportionate outcomes.  In fact it would only attest my point, that Indians, even the leadership, are making emotional decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investing money in these areas without any change in culture would be imprudent, because the money would not be spent on research. It would be spent on activities with an emotional component. And even a small amount of emotional component would lead to cognitive biases—either created within the researchers or used by them to manipulate the research reviewers.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Cornell note taking system</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/009/" />
    <updated>2025-07-03T19:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/009/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had come across a very useful and interesting way to take notes, &lt;a href=&quot;https://lsc.cornell.edu/how-to-study/taking-notes/cornell-note-taking-system/&quot;&gt;the Cornell note taking system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the philosophy of it and used it to take notes in some non-Math courses.  Here&#39;s what you do, you divide a page into three sections, by creating a left margin, a bottom margin and the main area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the main area of the page you write the notes, in the left margin you write the questions that the notes in the main area is answering.  In the bottom margin you summarize the overall idea of the notes on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it a pretty useful way to take notes and also a good way to think about anything new that we want to do.  Before doing something, we can ask ourselves why we are doing it, and after doing it we can reflect on our actions and think about what we have done and how it fits in the overall scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this note-taking method, we understand an idea in the notes from three points of view.  The idea as expressed by the teacher which we note in the main division of the page, our own understanding of what questions does the conveyed idea answers and our reflection regarding how the matter discussed in class fits in the overall scheme of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, note that since English is written left to right and top to bottom, the left margin is chosen to write questions.  IMO, this is done since the questions answered by the notes are generally pretty short and the questions can be horizontally aligned with the notes in the main-divison so that it is contextually clear which questions are answered by which parts of the notes.  The bottom margin is left for the summary because it relates to the whole page and how it fits in the context of notes on the other pages.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>&quot;A perfect language&quot;</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/008/" />
    <updated>2025-07-03T08:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/008/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How would a &amp;quot;perfect language&amp;quot; be created? By &amp;quot;perfect&amp;quot;, I mean a language that is independent of time and space. By independent of time, I mean that it cannot be refined further, i.e. it can be understood across time and by independent of space I mean the pronunciation can only change due to human error, not due to people having different &amp;quot;accents&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most natural languages are learnt by hearing others speak.  Like when a baby is born, the parents teach it the language it hears from them. However, a &amp;quot;perfect language&amp;quot; would not need a speaker to learn from.  Note that it can be learned from a speaker as well, just that it wouldn&#39;t necessarily &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a speaker to learn from.  It can be learned without hearing any sound whatsoever. It would be like how Math is done, i.e. it would be created and can be learned in silence, not how English and other common languages were created and are learned using words that are spoken in certain areas or by certain people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like there is an objective method of deriving Math results from silence by anyone, there must be some methods of deriving sounds for specific ideas by anyone using those rules from the absence of sound, i.e. silence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, one should not need hear anything in order to speak the language perfectly.  Then it would be the language of the Gods, or a &amp;quot;perfect langauge&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How will the idea of &amp;quot;something&amp;quot;, X, existing in time t1 be communicated across to time t2 where it doesn&#39;t exist?  There are two points here, one is that X, just like in Math, needs to be defined using the language before being used so that X is freed-from the contextual knowledge at t1. And if X doesn&#39;t need any context-freeing then it represents an idea that is timeless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, approximately, the whole point of the language is that it should be free from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&quot;&gt;System 1&lt;/a&gt; and should only need System 2 to understand and create it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why is India not participating in PISA?</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/006/" />
    <updated>2025-06-28T15:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/006/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;India has not been participating in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecd.org/en/about/programmes/pisa/pisa-participants.html&quot;&gt;PISA since 2009&lt;/a&gt;.  Here&#39;s an archived India Today&#39;s report on that matter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250324105225/https://www.indiatoday.in/education-today/news/story/india-may-drop-out-of-international-student-assessment-pisa-again-2692495-2025-03-12&quot;&gt;India may drop out of international student assessment PISA again - India Today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&#39;s PISA?  According to their website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PISA is the OECD&#39;s Programme for International Student Assessment. PISA
measures 15-year-olds’ ability to use their reading, mathematics and science
knowledge and skills to meet real-life challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After being ranked 72nd out of 73 countries in 2009, beating Kazakhstan with &amp;quot;great success&amp;quot;, India stopped participating in PISA.  Indian officials cited two main reasons for the withdrawal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;cultural disconnect&amp;quot;: Probably meaning that India has a different pedagogical philosophy than the &amp;quot;West&amp;quot;.  China was ranked 1 in 2009, BTW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misinformation regarding the language of examination:  In &#39;09 students thought that the only language they could take the exam was English.  So they didn&#39;t perform well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, India was to reengage with PISA, and had decided to take the 2021 test.  The officials made sure that the misinformation regarding the language is clarified, they also chose a few schools that would participate (generally the schools are chosen from a list of eligible schools by PISA&#39;s organizing body), and also made sure that a few questions about India are included in the exams so that the students could improve their performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Corona hit in 2021 and it was decided to reengage in 2025.  But now it looks like it may never happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why would a country which is never in the bottom 2 percentile in any other international exams like the International Math/Physics/Chemistry Olympiads, GRE, TOEFL, etc. perform differently in PISA?  There is a &amp;quot;cultural disconnect&amp;quot; in these exams as well, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my hypothesis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the other international exams mentioned are taken by candidates who specially prepare for those examinations. In Olympiads a team of 6 highly trained students represents a country, and GRE, TOEFL are taken by individuals who prepare for them specially.  In contrast, for the PISA exam however, each country draws a sample (randomly?) of 5000 students, as mentioned on the wiki, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Programme_for_International_Student_Assessment#Sampling&quot;&gt;Programme for International Student Assessment - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fulfill OECD requirements, each country must draw a sample of at least 5,000 students. In small countries like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iceland&quot; title=&quot;Iceland&quot;&gt;Iceland&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luxembourg&quot; title=&quot;Luxembourg&quot;&gt;Luxembourg&lt;/a&gt;,
where there are fewer than 5,000 students per year, an entire age
cohort is tested. Some countries used much larger samples than required
to allow comparisons between regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, because of the representation by five thousand students, the exam measures the average quality of education in schools, which I believe is why India is in the bottom 2 percent.  There is a lot of talk about the IIT alumni doing well in academics outside India, but they do not represent the average education in India which exams like PISA test.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>&quot;The problem with India&quot;</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/005/" />
    <updated>2025-06-28T13:58:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/005/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A former classmate wrote on LinkedIn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with India is that for every one guy  working 8 hours a day,
there are 10 willing to do 16 hours and it becomes the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I agree with what he said, his observation can be analyzed further.  He&#39;s
assuming that the only way to measure productivity is the number of hours
invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the age of machines this model of measuring productivity doesn&#39;t hold.  For
example, the sum total of the number of hours invested by all the employees to
create the first iteration of Google search would be much less than the sum
total of the time saved by the them (and the users) to search websites they
were looking for using Google search. The creation of a search engine would
lead to an increase in productivity in the long-term. This is true for many
software tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example that comes to mind is that of, vim. Very creative software
engineers who created tools like vim ended up saving millions of hours in text
editing for themselves and for other engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My former-batchmate&#39;s model of estimating productivity doesn&#39;t take into
account the amount of time saved by working for fewer hours but doing creative
work, which ends up saving a lot of time in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other point to keep in mind is that the cause of creativity is boredom.  If
one is always doing repetitive work and does not have any free time to reflect,
they will not be creative. So, I think &amp;quot;the problem with India&amp;quot; is that the
Indian companies don&#39;t know how to nurture or leverage creativity, and have a
wrong model of measuring productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>