<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mmanu Chaturvedi&#39;s blog.</title>
  <subtitle>This is where Mmanu writes.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/" />
  <updated>2025-07-03T19:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Mmanu Chaturvedi</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Cornell note taking system</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/009/" />
    <updated>2025-07-03T19:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/009/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had come across a very useful and interesting way to take notes.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://lsc.cornell.edu/how-to-study/taking-notes/cornell-note-taking-system/&quot;&gt;The Cornell note-taking system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the philosophy of it and used it to take notes in some non-Math courses.  Here&#39;s what you do, you divide a page into three sections, by creating a left margin, a bottom margin and the main area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the main area of the page you write the notes, in the left margin you write the questions that the notes in the main area is answering.  In the bottom margin you summarize the overall idea of the notes on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it a pretty useful way to take notes and also a good way to think about anything new.  Before doing something, we can ask ourselves why we are doing it, and after doing it we can reflect on our actions and think about what we have done and how it fits in the overall scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this note-taking method, we understand an idea in the notes from three points of view.  The idea as expressed by the teacher which we note in the main division of the page, our own understanding of what questions does the conveyed idea answers and our reflection regarding how the matter discussed in class fits in the overall scheme of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, note that since English is written left to right and top to bottom, the left margin is chosen to write questions.  IMO, this is done since the questions answered by the notes are generally pretty short and the questions can be horizontally aligned with the notes in the main-divison so that it is contextually clear which questions are answered by which parts of the notes.  The bottom margin is left for the summary because it relates to the whole page and how it fits in the context of notes in the other pages.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>&quot;A perfect language&quot;</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/008/" />
    <updated>2025-07-03T08:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/008/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How would a &amp;quot;perfect language&amp;quot; be created? By &amp;quot;perfect&amp;quot;, I mean a language that is independent of time and space. By independent of time, I mean that it cannot be refined further, i.e. it can be understood across time and by independent of space I mean the pronunciation can only change due to human error, not due to people having different &amp;quot;accents&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most natural languages are learnt by hearing others speak.  Like when a baby is born, the parents teach it the language it hears from them. However, a &amp;quot;perfect language&amp;quot; would not need a speaker to learn from.  Note that it can be learned from a speaker as well, just that it wouldn&#39;t necessarily &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a speaker to learn from.  It can be learned without hearing any sound whatsoever. It would be like how Math is done, i.e. it would be created and can be learned in silence, not how English and other common languages were created and are learned using words that are spoken in certain areas or by certain people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like there is an objective method of deriving Math results from silence by anyone, there must be some methods of deriving sounds for specific ideas by anyone using those rules from the absence of sound, i.e. silence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, one should not need hear anything in order to speak the language perfectly.  Then it would be the language of the Gods, or a &amp;quot;perfect langauge&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How will the idea of &amp;quot;something&amp;quot;, X, existing in time t1 be communicated across to time t2 where it doesn&#39;t exist?  There are two points here, one is that X, just like in Math, needs to be defined using the language before being used so that X is freed-from the contextual knowledge at t1. And if X doesn&#39;t need any context-freeing then it represents an idea that is timeless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, approximately, the whole point of the language is that it should be free from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&quot;&gt;System 1&lt;/a&gt; and should only need System 2 to understand and create it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why is India not participating in PISA?</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/006/" />
    <updated>2025-06-28T15:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/006/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;India has not been participating in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecd.org/en/about/programmes/pisa/pisa-participants.html&quot;&gt;PISA since 2009&lt;/a&gt;.  Here&#39;s an archived India Today&#39;s report on that matter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20250324105225/https://www.indiatoday.in/education-today/news/story/india-may-drop-out-of-international-student-assessment-pisa-again-2692495-2025-03-12&quot;&gt;India may drop out of international student assessment PISA again - India Today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what&#39;s PISA?  According to their website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PISA is the OECD&#39;s Programme for International Student Assessment. PISA
measures 15-year-olds’ ability to use their reading, mathematics and science
knowledge and skills to meet real-life challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After being ranked 72nd out of 73 countries in 2009, beating Kazakhstan with &amp;quot;great success&amp;quot;, India stopped participating in PISA.  Indian officials cited two main reasons for the withdrawal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;cultural disconnect&amp;quot;: Probably meaning that India has a different pedagogical philosophy than the &amp;quot;West&amp;quot;.  China was ranked 1 in 2009, BTW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misinformation regarding the language of examination:  In &#39;09 students thought that the only language they could take the exam was English.  So they didn&#39;t perform well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, India was to reengage with PISA, and had decided to take the 2021 test.  The officials made sure that the misinformation regarding the language is clarified, they also chose a few schools that would participate (generally the schools are chosen from a list of eligible schools by PISA&#39;s organizing body), and also made sure that a few questions about India are included in the exams so that the students could improve their performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Corona hit in 2021 and it was decided to reengage in 2025.  But now it looks like it may never happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, why would a country which is never in the bottom 2 percentile in any other international exams like the International Math/Physics/Chemistry Olympiads, GRE, TOEFL, etc. perform differently in PISA?  There is a &amp;quot;cultural disconnect&amp;quot; in these exams as well, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my hypothesis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the other international exams mentioned are taken by candidates who specially prepare for those examinations. In Olympiads a team of 6 highly trained students represents a country, and GRE, TOEFL are taken by individuals who prepare for them specially.  In contrast, for the PISA exam however, each country draws a sample (randomly?) of 5000 students, as mentioned on the wiki, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Programme_for_International_Student_Assessment#Sampling&quot;&gt;Programme for International Student Assessment - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fulfill OECD requirements, each country must draw a sample of at least 5,000 students. In small countries like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iceland&quot; title=&quot;Iceland&quot;&gt;Iceland&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luxembourg&quot; title=&quot;Luxembourg&quot;&gt;Luxembourg&lt;/a&gt;,
where there are fewer than 5,000 students per year, an entire age
cohort is tested. Some countries used much larger samples than required
to allow comparisons between regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, because of the representation by five thousand students, the exam measures the average quality of education in schools, which I believe is why India is in the bottom 2 percent.  There is a lot of talk about the IIT alumni doing well in academics outside India, but they do not represent the average education in India which exams like PISA test.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>&quot;The problem with India&quot;</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/005/" />
    <updated>2025-06-28T13:58:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/005/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A former classmate wrote on LinkedIn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with India is that for every one guy  working 8 hours a day,
there are 10 willing to do 16 hours and it becomes the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I agree with what he said, his observation can be analyzed further.  He&#39;s
assuming that the only way to measure productivity is the number of hours
invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the age of machines this model of measuring productivity doesn&#39;t hold.  For
example, the sum total of the number of hours invested by all the employees to
create the first iteration of Google search would be much less than the sum
total of the time saved by the them (and the users) to search websites they
were looking for using Google search. The creation of a search engine would
lead to an increase in productivity in the long-term. This is true for many
software tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example that comes to mind is that of, vim. Very creative software
engineers who created tools like vim ended up saving millions of hours in text
editing for themselves and for other engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My former-batchmate&#39;s model of estimating productivity doesn&#39;t take into
account the amount of time saved by working for fewer hours but doing creative
work, which ends up saving a lot of time in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other point to keep in mind is that the cause of creativity is boredom.  If
one is always doing repetitive work and does not have any free time to reflect,
they will not be creative. So, I think &amp;quot;the problem with India&amp;quot; is that the
Indian companies don&#39;t know how to nurture or leverage creativity, and have a
wrong model of measuring productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>&#39;Working very hard&#39; and programming</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/004/" />
    <updated>2025-06-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/004/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across this Zen story, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sofoarchon.com/10-short-zen-stories/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A martial arts student went to his teacher and said earnestly, “I am devoted to studying your martial system.
How long will it take me to master it.” The teacher’s reply was casual, “Ten years.” Impatiently, the student answered,
“But I want to master it faster than that. I will work very hard. I will practice every day, ten or more hours a day if I have to. How long will it take then?”
The teacher thought for a moment, “20 years.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems to be true for programming as well. If a programming task needs to be finished quickly because of some underlying reason which comes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;thinking fast&amp;quot;, instead of &amp;quot;thinking slow&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, it cannot be finished at the expected rate, because one would start creating work by introducing bugs and finishing the task would take more time than it would have if there wasn&#39;t a need of finishing it at speed.  There must be some XKCD for this which I can&#39;t find.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ghalib on transactional love, futility and ego.</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/003/" />
    <updated>2025-06-22T17:04:29Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/003/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;ghalib-on-transactional-love&quot;&gt;Ghalib on transactional love:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
dil us ko pahle hī nāz-o-adā se de baiṭhe &lt;br&gt;
hameñ dimāġh kahāñ ḥusn ke taqāẓā kā
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
Phir shauq kar raha hai khareed-dar ki talab,&lt;br&gt;
Arz-e-mataa-e-akl-o-jaan kiye hue
&lt;p&gt;Bik jaate hein hum aap mataa-e-sukhan ke saath,&lt;br&gt;
Lekin ayaar-e-tabaa-e-khareed-daar dekh kar
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;ghalib-on-futility&quot;&gt;Ghalib on futility:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
yih jāntā hūñ kih tū aur pāsuḳh-e maktūb &lt;br&gt;
magar sitam-zadah hūñ żauq-e ḳhāmah-farsā kā
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reminds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
Humko maloom hai jannat ki haqiqat lekin,&lt;br&gt;
Dil ke khush rakhne ko Ghalib ye khayal achcha hai
&lt;p&gt;Khat likhenge garche matlab kuch na ho,&lt;br&gt;
Hum to ashiq hein tumhaare naam ke
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;ghalib-on-ego&quot;&gt;Ghalib on ego:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
ḳhvud-parastī se rahe bā-ham-digar nā-āshnā&lt;br&gt;
bekasī merī sharīk āʾīnah terā āshnā
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rekhta.org/ghazals/niyaaz-o-naaz-ke-jhagde-mitaae-jaate-hain-jigar-moradabadi-ghazals&quot;&gt;Rekhta page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Ghalibian impasse!</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/002/" />
    <updated>2025-06-22T17:04:29Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/002/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unhe saval pah zum-e-junoon hai, kyun ladiye&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Hamen jawab se qat-e-nazar hai, kya kahiye&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She gets mad at my asking questions what&#39;s the point of fighting?  I get
embarrassed by her answering, what can I say?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it&#39;s not the questions that make her mad, and the answers that
embarrass me, but it&#39;s my questioning that makes her mad, and her answering is
what I find embarrassing.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://franpritchett.com/00ghalib/201/201_07.html&quot;&gt;Prichett&#39;s page for the couplet.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reminds me of Jigar (1st couplet):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;niyāz o naaz ke jhagḌe miTā.e jaate haiñ&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ham un meñ aur vo ham meñ samā.e jaate haiñ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rekhta.org/ghazals/niyaaz-o-naaz-ke-jhagde-mitaae-jaate-hain-jigar-moradabadi-ghazals&quot;&gt;Rekhta page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome!</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/001/" />
    <updated>2025-06-22T13:01:07Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/001/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my blog! This marks the beginning.  I will be importing posts from my
previous blog here.  I will be posting about poetry, philosophy, software
engineering, Indian classical music, and films. Instead of suffering through the
noise of social media, I decided to document my interests here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>