<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mmanu Chaturvedi&#39;s blog.</title>
  <subtitle>This is where Mmanu writes.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/" />
  <updated>2025-11-14T04:18:30Z</updated>
  <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Mmanu Chaturvedi</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>How to generate profits by exploiting human instincts?</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/022/" />
    <updated>2025-11-14T04:18:30Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/022/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post we discuss how we can go about exploiting human instincts to generate profits.
Note that all these are System 1 artifacts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow&quot;&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/a&gt;), that&#39;s why we call them instincts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spot the emotions: Now, the first step towards the goal is to spot the emotions. The emotions may already be present or can be generated.
The common way to generate emotions is via advertising. Advertisements can create different emotions in the viewers by methods like employing celebrities, insulting the competition,
making sure what&#39;s being sold is cool and hip, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of note is that sometimes the emotions may already be present. Like when one is in a hospital, or a loved one is sick.
Or when one is undergoing a divorce, or a pandemic is underway, or when one is happy to move into a new house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paradoxically enough, sometimes, you can create emotions by selling a product. Like a product can be cleverly designed to
give a sense of incompleteness when it&#39;s bought. This emotion is commonly used to sell add-ons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use more sinister means to create emotions, like making an entire population feel inadequate due to their skin color, culture, etc.
This is wonderfully illustrated by imperial powers, and products like skin-creams, language classes, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a product: Once you have spotted the emotions, by either generating them or spotting the already present ones, you are halfway there.
Now, all you need to do is cleverly design a product that can leverage those emotions for profits.
You need to make sure that the product is priced according to the intensity and urgency of the emotion spotted. Note that the product could be an abstraction.
Some examples:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Emotion&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Product&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Happiness of moving into a new house.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Overcharging for a security deposit transaction compared to banks.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sadness of undergoing a divorce, or a break-up.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Short-term relationships, platonic friends morphing into friends with benefits.  Tinder, etc.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Attracting the opposite-sex via olfactory means.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A deodorant or perfume.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Want to get money for research.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;PhD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Boredom because you can&#39;t sustain solitude.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Events to socialize.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that ALL products sold have emotions or instincts behind them that they are exploiting, because if there are no emotions you go
in a state of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samadhi&quot;&gt;Samadhi and have a want for nothing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On setting context and exerting power</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/021/" />
    <updated>2025-11-07T04:19:30Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/021/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post, we want to discuss one of the most subtle ways of exerting power. This way of exerting power often leads to people saying, &amp;quot;This is how things are; we just need to accept it.&amp;quot; Note that we are not criticizing anything, just observing neutrally how things are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start by observing how Nature exerts its power over us. Nature exerts its power over us through its laws. For example, if we jump from a tall mountain, the law of gravity ensures that we die. If we go into the cold without being sufficiently dressed for a long time, Nature exerts its power using the laws of thermodynamics and ensures that we die of hypothermia. We observe that Nature exerts its power over us by setting the context in which we operate. It sets the context via the laws that we must abide by if we want to exist. In addition, its laws make sure that we have the will to exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to Nature is how different groups, institutions, societal constructs, etc., exert power as well. The context set by these institutions determines how their members behave. For example, the laws of capitalism set the context in which a CEO operates. When inaugurating a product, they need to make sure that they don’t point out the shortcomings of the product they are trying to sell; the laws ensure that they work within that context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A researcher works in a similar way with regard to research, they need to work while keeping in mind the funding agency that’s funding their research and sell their research like a CEO selling a product. Research, however, cannot have any emotional component; it just has to be understood neutrally like a law. Selling research, however, does, it is subservient to the laws of capitalism. So wherever there is a conflict between the laws of capitalism and the laws of Nature, the researcher needs to leverage the emotions, and thus the cognitive biases, of the audience to sell the research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the laws that set the context are unspoken, like in the case of a group of friends. Those laws decide what is polite behavior, what subjects are too sensitive to be spoken about, what causes need to be supported, etc. These unspoken rules are referred to as context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entity that creates the laws, spoken and unspoken, sets the context in which the members operate and exerts power over them. We say that this is a subtle way of exerting power because many times, the entity&#39;s influence can be so expansive that the members can say nothing but, &amp;quot;This is how things work.&amp;quot;. Note that the entity could be an individual, a group of people such as a committee, or even an abstraction like greed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On questioning</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/020/" />
    <updated>2025-11-01T04:17:30Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/020/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post, we would try to understand how to ask a question. We believe that in order to know the answer to any question, we need to understand how to ask a question. Like we discussed &lt;a href=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/017/&quot;&gt;in the previous post&lt;/a&gt;, when we analyze something, i.e., use only our minds to interact with an idea, the origin of the idea is in its complement; similarly, the origin of an answer is in its complement, that is, the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, when we ask a question, we are already expecting a certain answer. Like when we ask if it&#39;s going to rain tonight, we already have in our subconscious the current season, the climatic patterns of the place we are living in, etc., which make us biased towards a specific answer. A simple way to observe this is by trying to guess an answer to the question, with the same consciousness in which the question was asked. If, in our minds, there&#39;s a certain answer that we expect, then we have not actually asked the question if it&#39;s going to rain; we actually have asked whether our guess is correct or not, because our mind wasn&#39;t totally neutral when asking the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we had bias in our minds, we haven&#39;t yet arrived at the origin of the answer; that is, we haven&#39;t really asked the question whether it&#39;s going to rain. Until we can ask a question in a state of mind that is free from all bias, Nature will not tell us the answer to the question. And as soon as we ask the question in an unbiased way, we will have a complement to the question, which is the answer, created in our minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a common mistake we make when asking questions: we don&#39;t ask them in a neutral way, and we are prone to all manner of cognitive biases.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In praise of the Unix Philosophy - 1</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/019/" />
    <updated>2025-10-13T04:15:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/019/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The philosophy of Unix has elements of other timeless philosophies. One of them is that its principles match with the
principles of design of the underlying elements. That is, the software design principles of the Unix philosophy match
with the philosophy with which the underlying hardware is built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we observe the elements of the logic design of chips that run the software, we observe that one of the core principles on which
the chips are designed is that they take a lot of very simple elements and then glue them together in creative ways. That is,
it is the gluing that is difficult to understand, not the elements themselves. In the case of chips, the elements are the logic gates,
and by using a large number of them in creative ways, the logic design of chips is done. The logic gates themselves are, of course,
very easy to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s first observe the philosophy of logic gates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They do very simple computations. The AND, OR, and NOT gates all do very simple-to-understand computations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They are easy to combine. It’s easy to combine logic gates to create complicated structures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their inputs and outputs are simple to understand, i.e., the substructures of the complicated structures can be debugged.
They have at most two inputs and one output, all 0 or 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can see how they match with the tenets of the Unix philosophy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do one thing and do it well&lt;/strong&gt;: Similar to the gates, i.e., the software tools themselves shouldn’t be doing too many things.
We can observe this clearly in GNU utilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programs should work together&lt;/strong&gt;: Shell is the underlying glue in Unix. Powerful utilities like pipes let programmers
combine the software tools in creative ways to accomplish powerful computational tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text should be the universal interface of the programs&lt;/strong&gt;: This, just like logic gates, makes debugging substructures easier.
This is easy to see while debugging a Bash script. Since the inputs and outputs can be printed as text on the terminal,
having text as the interface makes debugging easier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see that there some similarities in the two philosophies.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to Show Work’s Getting Done Without Doing Any: Workplace Learnings of Sweden for Make Benefit Other Glorious Nations</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/018/" />
    <updated>2025-10-04T08:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/018/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is what I learned while working in Sweden about how to show that you&#39;re working a lot without actually doing any work.  Credit where credit is due, I met a bunch of scientists there who taught me the effectiveness of these lessons, inadvertently, perhaps.  They used these to great effect for many years!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplemental reading: Any good book about cognitive biases.  Recommended one: &lt;a href=&quot;https://youarenotsosmart.com/&quot;&gt;You Are Not So Smart&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Steve Jobs method: Always do all the announcements.  Most people think the person who does the announcements has done all the work.  This is so common that &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/FmbwR9J6-Yw?si=iRgVIgPaNmzjMR5Q&quot;&gt;Bill Burr even has a joke on this&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s like &#39;Kill the messenger&#39;, except the sentiment is the opposite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use fancy words: Invent fancy words to describe what you&#39;re doing.  Don&#39;t use commonly used words.  This is a common practice in industries like management, finance, etc., but can be used in software engineering as well.  The benefits are twofold, one is that there is an automatic formation of a guild which knows the meaning of those words, the second is that the people outside the team hearing those words feel like they don&#39;t know what you&#39;re talking about.  You need to find some other people who don&#39;t do any work to form the guild for this one, though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find experts and gaslight them: This is a very important strategy in order to not let everyone know that you&#39;re doing little work.  If the people who actually do the work come into the limelight your status would be revealed.  This is best done in groups, a good strategy is to isolate the people actually doing the work, and then try to gaslight them so that they don&#39;t notice your lack of work-ethic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Address people never the problem:  This is a great strategy to stymie any discussion, and exploiting personal weaknesses of others&#39; to your advantage.  If there&#39;s a problem being discussed never do that in a neutral and objective way, always be subjective, this is especially useful when you&#39;re being assigned tasks.  Believe in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Straw_man&quot;&gt;robustness of the Straw Man&lt;/a&gt;!  This has multiple benefits, one is that the discussion turns emotional, another is that it gives a chance to attack people who actually work personally.  Note that if the culture allows, sexuality can be very effectively employed for maintaining subjectivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always speak a lot in meetings:  Most people think that people doing the speaking are working a lot.  Be very attentive and vocal in meetings, this creates a bias in the minds of the people that don&#39;t actually know what&#39;s happening in team. Don&#39;t forget to speak loudly, speak fast and speak over others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Present and remind others of your work repeatedly: There are a few nuances to this strategy.  First of all, always prioritize demos and presentations over actual work.  Secondly, always overlap already done work with new work in presentations, creating more volume everytime.  Thirdly, try to remind of your work repeatedly.  All these give an impression of you having done more work than you actually have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the workspace to your advantage: Stack books, strew papers, equipment, wires, etc., on and around your desk.  Stick post-it notes, cheat sheets, technical papers on the desk&#39;s walls.  This again gives the impression of productivity and concentration-induced absent-mindedness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, cognitive biases are your friend, starting from the CEO to the workers in the lowest rungs, exploiting cognitive biases is something that needs to be learned by all to thrive in the workplace!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How the origin of everything is from its complement</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/017/" />
    <updated>2025-09-22T02:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/017/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In order for any idea or material thing to be analyzed, i.e. understood with the mind, there has to be an abstract representation of it.  And as soon as an abstraction is created in our minds, there has to be a complement of the abstraction, in order for the abstraction to exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, let&#39;s say we want to analyze a pencil.  We will first create an abstract representation of the pencil in our minds, this can vary from person to person, but they have an abstraction for the pencil in their minds, nonetheless.  When that abstraction matches with an object, they call it a pencil.  Now, the complement of the pencil is the absence of pencil, there has to exist at least one abstract representation of the absence of the pencil.  Maybe it is the pencil-sized emptiness in the pencil box, maybe it&#39;s the empty space on the desk.  But there has to exist a representation of the absence of the pencil in our minds in order for it to detect a pencil.  In other words, the origin of a pencil&#39;s presence is from its absence, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can replace &#39;pencil&#39; in the above example, with any material thing or idea, even the whole reality we perceive with our minds.  The whole reality we perceive with our minds needs to have a complement, which makes us perceive the reality as it is.  Perhaps the force which doesn&#39;t let us understand the complement of reality is what is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maya_(religion)&quot;&gt;spoken about in Advaita Vedanta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The source of knowledge</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/016/" />
    <updated>2025-09-21T02:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/016/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whether the source of all knowledge is internal or external is what we wish to address in this write-up. We define knowledge as it is defined &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge&quot;&gt;colloquially&lt;/a&gt;. By external we mean whether knowledge comes from things external to us, like books, teachers, fellow-students, etc. and by internal we mean whether knowledge comes from within us, i.e., as a reaction to the things external to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s take an example of Newton&#39;s laws of motion. Does one need an external source of knowledge to arrive at the laws of motion?  The answer is no, reproducibility is a property of Science, so one could just observe how things move and arrive at them. One doesn&#39;t need any external source of knowledge, like books or professors, in order to learn Newton&#39;s laws of motion. It&#39;s just because we wish to save time that we have external sources like books, i.e. we wish to not re-invent the wheel, so to speak, and focus on learning &amp;quot;unknown&amp;quot; laws of Nature instead of &amp;quot;known&amp;quot; ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the laws of motion, one doesn&#39;t need any external source to learn any of Nature&#39;s laws. One could learn them by observing, questioning, and reflecting.  So, the source of knowledge is internal, not external.  This post is related to the previous post, &lt;a href=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/008/&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;A perfect language&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Cornell note-taking system and different groups of people</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/015/" />
    <updated>2025-09-14T05:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/015/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wrote about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/009/&quot;&gt;Cornell note-taking system&lt;/a&gt; in a previous post, and how I had found it quite an interesting way to take notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was wondering how it could be used to look at different kinds of people that inhabit the world. The equivalent of the main section of the notes would be the people who like to take instructions. They like to do what they are instructed to do, and what they see others doing—just taking notes. This, like the main section, would be the largest chunk of the world’s population. This population, akin to what the main section is used for, likes copying what others are doing without questioning or reflecting on it. This group is that of the common, non-scientific people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there is the group of people equivalent to the left margin. These would be the questioning types, who like to question everything consciously but do not necessarily reflect on it. This group would be like the average scientists and engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there would be the group of people who like to reflect on things but do not necessarily question them. This would be the bottom margin in the Cornell system. This group comprises of managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the group of people who like to both question things and reflect on them, on how they connect to the overall scheme of things. This group consists of the great philosophers, exceptional scientists, engineers, managers, diplomats, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How CEOs bullshit!</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/012/" />
    <updated>2025-09-05T12:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/012/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I was sharing with someone how CEOs bullshit, which led to this post. There are many videos available of CEOs of many companies announcing various things. So, it&#39;s easy to understand the thinking of CEOs at least as far as the product announcements go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s first define bullshitting. Bullshitting, for our purposes, is the opposite of being forthcoming. It&#39;s basically hiding the truth with a wrapper idea, really believing in the wrapper idea. Believing it with all your heart, to the point that you can convince everyone that the wrapper is the true intention of your actions and not the real truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that products CEOs sell are always useless. What I am saying is that there&#39;s always the real truth and the wrapper concealing it, and therein between the two lies bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now CEOs have to constantly cover the fact that they created a product because they can make a lot of money with the wrapper that the product is actually useful for society and customers. The fact that they are doing it for the money is not something that they will accept readily even when explicitly pointed out, it will be only known via the context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They will always have a complete and total belief in the product that they are selling, even if it&#39;s useless. They bullshit with total confidence their customers and listeners that it&#39;s not the fact that this product will make them profit that is the driving force but the fact that they believe that this product is useful for the customers.  They would look down upon their competition, however good that is, find faults in the competition&#39;s products and customers, make up personal stories and use other cognitive biases to promote their product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This style of bullshiting is close to how &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maya_(religion)&quot;&gt;Nature decieves us as well&lt;/a&gt;, that deserves a long write-up, though.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What the AI will not replace?</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/011/" />
    <updated>2025-09-01T16:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/011/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A discussion regarding what AI will not replace in software engineering led to
this post. AI cannot replace what it doesn&#39;t have, which is self-consciousness.
The mental manifestation of self-consciousness is reflection. And the physical
manifestation of it is the action which is taken after reflection (this, in my
opinion, is what is &#39;dharma&#39;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Dharma&#39; may mean different things in different fields. &#39;Dharma&#39; in the context of
software engineering is basically what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Douglas_McIlroy#Views_on_computing&quot;&gt;Dr. McIlroy had refered to as &#39;negative coding&#39;&lt;/a&gt;.
It&#39;s the process of removing code instead of adding it making the software simpler. (My own attempt &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/m-chaturvedi/undupes/&quot;&gt;at negative coding at design level.&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Dharma&#39; process can be explained very easily. If an action is taken without
reflection, it&#39;s not dharma, unless the instincts which are the cause of action
have been trained with the process which is created with reflection. This
process of training the instincts is commonly referred to as &#39;culture&#39;. So,
many a time, during code reviews, the software engineers would instinctually
know that a piece of code has problems. This is because of the &#39;culture&#39;, i.e.,
they have gone through so much code that they have refined their instincts with
the culture of software engineering &#39;dharma&#39;, so even without consciously
reflecting, they know that the piece of code that they are reviewing has a
problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI is trained with the latter method, that is, its &#39;instincts&#39; are being
refined to the extent that it starts doing things which come out of a lot of
reflection. So, it&#39;s trying to replicate the dharma of software engineering.
What it lacks is self-consciousness. What this means is that, unlike humans who
can remove a piece of code from what they wrote after reflecting on it, AI
cannot remove a piece of code from its own programming. That is, AI cannot do
negative coding on the code it created without interacting with any external
agents other than the code and its own programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be said in another way. Humans can evolve by just meditating like the
Buddha; a piece of program cannot just sit and evolve itself. Evolution is like
&#39;negative coding&#39;. And the final destination of &#39;negative coding&#39; is zeroness,
which, unlike the Buddha, computers cannot experience, or reach, or meditate
upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typos fixed using ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>