<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Mmanu Chaturvedi&#39;s blog.</title>
  <subtitle>This is where Mmanu writes.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/" />
  <updated>2025-06-28T13:58:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Mmanu Chaturvedi</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>&#39;The problem with India&#39;</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/005/" />
    <updated>2025-06-28T13:58:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/005/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A former classmate wrote on LinkedIn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The problem with India is that for every one guy  working 8 hours a day, there
are 10 willing to do 16 hours and it becomes the norm.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I agree with what he said, his observation can be analyzed further.  He&#39;s
assuming that the only way to measure productivity is the number of hours
invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the age of machines this model of measuring productivity doesn&#39;t hold.  For
example, the sum total of the number of hours invested by all the employees to
create the first iteration of Google search would be much less than the time
saved by the users to search websites they were looking for using Google search.
This is true for many software tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My former-batchmate&#39;s model of estimating productivity doesn&#39;t take into
account the amount of time saved by working for fewer hours but doing creative
work, which ends up saving a lot of time in the future. Another example that
comes to mind if that of, vim. Very creative software engineers who created
tools like vim ended up saving millions of hours in text editing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other point to keep in mind is that the cause of creativity is boredom.  If
one is always doing repetitive work and do not have any free time to reflect,
they will not be creative. So, I think &amp;quot;the problem with India&amp;quot; is that the
Indian companies don&#39;t know how to nurture or leverage creativity, and have a
wrong model of measuring the productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>&#39;Working very hard&#39; and programming</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/004/" />
    <updated>2025-06-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/004/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across this Zen story, &lt;a href=&quot;https://sofoarchon.com/10-short-zen-stories/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A martial arts student went to his teacher and said earnestly, “I am devoted to studying your martial system.
How long will it take me to master it.” The teacher’s reply was casual, “Ten years.” Impatiently, the student answered,
“But I want to master it faster than that. I will work very hard. I will practice every day, ten or more hours a day if I have to. How long will it take then?”
The teacher thought for a moment, “20 years.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems to be true for programming as well. If a programming task needs to be finished quickly because of some underlying reason which comes from &amp;quot;thinking fast&amp;quot;, instead of &amp;quot;thinking slow&amp;quot;, it cannot be finished at the expected rate, because one would start creating work by introducing bugs and finishing the task would take more time than it would have if there wasn&#39;t a need of finishing it at speed.  There must be some XKCD for this which I can&#39;t find.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ghalib on transactional love, futility and ego.</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/003/" />
    <updated>2025-06-22T17:04:29Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/003/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;ghalib-on-transactional-love&quot;&gt;Ghalib on transactional love:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
dil us ko pahle hī nāz-o-adā se de baiṭhe &lt;br&gt;
hameñ dimāġh kahāñ ḥusn ke taqāẓā kā
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
Phir shauq kar raha hai khareed-dar ki talab,&lt;br&gt;
Arz-e-mataa-e-akl-o-jaan kiye hue
&lt;p&gt;Bik jaate hein hum aap mataa-e-sukhan ke saath,&lt;br&gt;
Lekin ayaar-e-tabaa-e-khareed-daar dekh kar
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;ghalib-on-futility&quot;&gt;Ghalib on futility:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
yih jāntā hūñ kih tū aur pāsuḳh-e maktūb &lt;br&gt;
magar sitam-zadah hūñ żauq-e ḳhāmah-farsā kā
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reminds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
Humko maloom hai jannat ki haqiqat lekin,&lt;br&gt;
Dil ke khush rakhne ko Ghalib ye khayal achcha hai
&lt;p&gt;Khat likhenge garche matlab kuch na ho,&lt;br&gt;
Hum to ashiq hein tumhaare naam ke
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;ghalib-on-ego&quot;&gt;Ghalib on ego:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;i&gt;
ḳhvud-parastī se rahe bā-ham-digar nā-āshnā&lt;br&gt;
bekasī merī sharīk āʾīnah terā āshnā
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rekhta.org/ghazals/niyaaz-o-naaz-ke-jhagde-mitaae-jaate-hain-jigar-moradabadi-ghazals&quot;&gt;Rekhta page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Ghalibian impasse!</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/002/" />
    <updated>2025-06-22T17:04:29Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/002/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unhe saval pah zum-e-junoon hai, kyun ladiye&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Hamen jawab se qat-e-nazar hai, kya kahiye&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She gets mad at my asking questions what&#39;s the point of fighting?  I get
embarrassed by her answering, what can I say?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it&#39;s not the questions that make her mad, and the answers that
embarrass me, but it&#39;s my questioning that makes her mad, and her answering is
what I find embarrassing.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://franpritchett.com/00ghalib/201/201_07.html&quot;&gt;Prichett&#39;s page for the couplet.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reminds me of Jigar (1st couplet):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;niyāz o naaz ke jhagḌe miTā.e jaate haiñ&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ham un meñ aur vo ham meñ samā.e jaate haiñ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rekhta.org/ghazals/niyaaz-o-naaz-ke-jhagde-mitaae-jaate-hain-jigar-moradabadi-ghazals&quot;&gt;Rekhta page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Welcome!</title>
    <link href="https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/001/" />
    <updated>2025-06-22T13:01:07Z</updated>
    <id>https://m-chaturvedi.github.io/blog/001/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my blog! This marks the beginning.  I will be importing posts from my
previous blog here.  I will be posting about poetry, philosophy, software
engineering, Indian classical music, and films. Instead of suffering through the
noise of social media, I decided to document my interests here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>